Guide to the William Henry Owen Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Henry Owen papers
1881-1945
MS 380
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.75
(25 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, sermons, other writings, and memorabilia, concerning both Owen's personal life and his work as an Episcopal priest. The bulk of the papers is composed of sermons delivered from Owen's pulpit in Holy Trinity Church, New York City. Much of the correspondence is made up of letters from World War I and World War II servicemen from Owen's churches, letters from fellow Episcopal clergy, or correspondence concerning Owen's coin collection. The papers also include Owen's inspirational writings and drafts for his memoirs.
Owen, William Henry, 1874-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William H. Owen, 1934-1940 and of his estate, 1944-1945.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1881-1944. II. Sermons, 1923-1944. III. Other Writings, Notes, and Memorabilia, 1887-1945.
Scope and Contents
The William Henry Owen Papers contain correspondence, sermons, other writings, and memorabilia documenting both the personal life and friendships of William Henry Owen and his work as a priest in the Protestant Episcopal Church in New York. The bulk of the papers date from Owen's rectorship at Holy Trinity Church in New York City. The papers are arranged in three series.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, is composed of Owen's letters from family, friends, and other Episcopal clergymen; correspondence with Yale University concerning Owen's coin collection; and four boxes of letters from servicemen during World Wars I and II. The servicemen represented were, for the most part, Owen' s parishioners writing their minister about personal feelings and experiences in the wars. Filed with the World War I era letters are some examples of camp or ship periodicals and trench cards. Included in the correspondence with family, friends, and clergymen are discussions of church business and ecclesiastical affairs in New York City. Correspondence with Yale University contains some of Owen's annual reports as associate curator of coins in the library.
Series II, SERMONS, comprises a numerical run of approximately 500 of Owen's sermons delivered from the time he assumed the position of rector at Holy Trinity Church until less than two months before his death. The sermons are handwritten on loose sheets of paper, and at the beginning of each is a form showing the sermon number, text, topic, season, date originally delivered, and other dates and locations for preaching the same sermon.
Series III, OTHER WRITINGS, NOTES, AND MEMORABILIA, includes student essays, sermons not part of the numerical sequence in Series II, lectures and talks to church and non-church groups, and talks on coin collecting and the Yale Numismatic Collection. The files also encompass Owen's recollections of people and events in his life and drafts of his memoir "Reactions to Life," 1939. At the end of the series are a few folders of notes on topics relating to coins and to church work and some items of memorabilia and memorial tributes.
The William Henry Owen Papers were given to the Yale University Library between 1934 and 1945 by Owen and by his estate. For many years the papers were physically divided between the Manuscripts and Archives Department and the Beinecke Rare Book Library. The papers were reassembled as one collection in Manuscripts and Archives in 1983.
Biographical / Historical
William Henry Owen was born in New York City in 1874, the son of William Henry and Mary Lavinia Brooks Owen. He had one sister, Mary Lavinia Owen Borden. He received a B.A. from Yale University in 1897 and an M.A. in 1899.
In 1901 he graduated from the General Theological Seminary and was ordained a priest in the Protestant Episcopal Church. For five years he served an assistantship at St. Thomas Church, New York, before assuming the position of rector at Trinity Church, Mount Vernon, New York, in 1906. Here he served until 1922 when he became rector of Holy Trinity Church in New York City. Owen remained at Holy Trinity until his retirement in 1937. He was also a trustee of the Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine and was awarded the degree of Doctor of Sacred Theology by the General Theological Seminary in 1936.
Owen was a life-long collector of coins, and in 1927 he donated his valuable collection to Yale University. From 1931 until his death Owen worked as associate curator of coins in the Yale University Library. Owen died at his summer residence at Natural Bridge, Virginia, on May 27, 1944.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Coins -- Collectors and collecting; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives; Mount Vernon (Westchester County, N.Y.) -- Religious and ecclesiastical institutions; New York (N.Y.) -- Religious and ecclesiastical institutions; Memoirs; Sermons; Clergy; Borden, Mary Lavinia; Chorley, E. Clowes (Edward Clowes), 1865-1949; Coffin, Henry Sloane, 1877-1954; Cummins, Alexander Griswold, 1869-1946; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Gates, Milo; Manning, William Thomas, Bp., 1866-1949; Owen, Lewis; Owen, William Henry, 1874-; Robbins, Howard Chandler, 1876-1952; Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine (New York, N.Y.); Episcopal Church -- Clergy -- Correspondence, reminiscences, etc.; Holy Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.); Trinity Church (Mount Vernon, N.Y.); Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University. Numismatic Collection -- Library
- Correspondence, 1881-1944; Series I; 1.75 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is arranged in three sections: General, World War I, and World War II. General includes all correspondence with family, friends, and other Episcopal clergymen. World War I contains all correspondence for World War I era servicemen; the contents of World War II is likewise for World War II era servicemen. Each section is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General
    - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Borden, Mary Lavinia (Owen) and Bertram, 1928-1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - C (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chorley, Edward Clowes and Florence, 1919-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Coffin, Henry Sloane, 1896-1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cummins, Alexander, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cushing, Harvey and Kate, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - D (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - E (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - F (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - G (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Gates, Milo, 1928-1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - H (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - J (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - K (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - L (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - M (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Manning, William T., 1918-1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - N (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - O (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Owen, 1881-1897, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Owen, Lewis, 1917-1940 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - P (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - R (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Robbins, Howard C., 1917-1942 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - S (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - T (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - U (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - W (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Yale University, 1933-1944 (Box 1, Folder 31-33)
    - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Owen's notes on the correspondence (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - World War I
    - Anderson, Milton T. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Arduin, Joseph R. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - B (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - C (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Dummett, Arthur R. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Fa - Fe (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Finnerman, Thomas G. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Finnerman, William (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Geiger, Francis J. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Griffiths, Stanley A. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Groves, Adrian D. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Groves, Lester G. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Gutierrez, W. Kemeys (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Harris, Thomas L. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Hayes, Albert (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Hayward, A.B. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Hayward, Edward C. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Hayward, John M. (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Hayward, Robert B. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Hayward, William W. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Hickcock, Edward D. (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Johnson, C. Wadsworth (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Ketchum, Chester (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Koerbell, William G., Jr. (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Kurzhals, Edward (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Kurzhals, Frederick C. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Kurzhals, Jacob A. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Leary, Arthur G. (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Leary, Cornelius (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Lees, Charles L. (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Lefebvre, Channing W. (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Lennon, Jack D. (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Lennon, John F. (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Leviness, William (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Martin, Howard J. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Mason, Walter R. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Menkel, William (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Millis, Otto Y. (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Morange, Irving S. (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Morange, Leonard S. (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Mulford, Allen (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Myers, Oscar B. (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Nichols, Malcolm G. (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Ozmon, Richard W. (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Packman, Collin J. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Packman, Earl G. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Packman, Harold L. (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Penfield, Carlyle (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Peterson, Clinton S. (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Peterson, Robert S. (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Phipps, Edward L.E. (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Phipps, Francis H. (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Pick, Bernard G. (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Pinney, Ray W.C. (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Platt, Thomas W. (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Plumb, Hugh H. (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Robinson, Beverly K. (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Robinson, E.A. (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Robson, May G. (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Roche, James M (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Scarlett, Albert E. (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Schiele, Harold W. (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Siddle, Longsden H. (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Skannel, Harold V. (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Slawter, Archibald C. (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Taylor, Herbert V. (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Theall, Harold (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Theall, Walter (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Thorne, Frederick P. (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Tucker, Gilbert E (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Twaddell, C.O. (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Van Brunt, Charles B. (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Van Keuren, Frederick F. (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Van Norden, Jay H. (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Van Pelt, George W. (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Vaughan, George W., Jr. (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Vaughan, James M. (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Vaughan, Ralph (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Weimar, Edward W., Jr. (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Wilsey, Grove E. (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Wintermeyer, Lewis H. (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Woomer, Harold P. (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - World War II
    - A (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Baldinger, O.M. (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Ballentine, David (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Ballentine, Hugh (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Ballentine, Robert (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Ballentine, William (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Ban - Bar (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Bl - Bu (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Bernardin, Joseph B. (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Carreras, Cecil (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Clark, William C. (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Christensen, Richard (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Co - Cr (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - D (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Eager, Theodore, R., Jr. (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Edmonson, Charles (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Fainter, J.C. (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Fi - Fl (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Ga- Gl (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - God - Gon (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Ha - He (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Hope, Benjamin B. (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Hughes, Richard (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Hughes, Robert (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - K (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Layne, Emmitt T., Jr. (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Lea, Robert L. (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Li - Lo (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Lucas, James L. (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Lucas, John J. (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Luskado, Garland (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - McAvoy, George (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - McAvoy, Henry D. (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - McAvoy, Richard (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Meyer, J. Pennington (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Mitchell, Robert W. (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Muller, John F. (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - Ogden, George C. (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - Owen, Harry G. (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - Owens, Frank C. (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - Pe -Pl (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Rei - Rey (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Rice, Frank (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Rice, Walter L. (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Roa - Roc (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Rompf, Everett (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Ryan, Carl M. (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Parker, Robert W. (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Samuelson, Joseph D. (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Sentelle, Gywn (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Smith, Donald P. (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Smith, Robert L. (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - T (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - V (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Walker, Elwood (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Watts, Herbert C. (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Williamson, Mac (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - Willis, Luther (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - Wilmer, Joseph (Box 5, Folder 149)
- Sermons, 1923-1944; Series II; 6.5 linear feet (16 boxes)
  SERMONS is arranged according to the numerical system established by Owen. Sermon number 700 is dated 1923 and the numbered sermons follow, more or less, in chronological order.
  - #700 - 736 (Box 6, Folder 150-156)
  - #737 - 768 (Box 7, Folder 157-163)
  - #769 - 797 (Box 8, Folder 164-171)
  - #798 - 824 (Box 9, Folder 172-179)
  - #825 - 854 (Box 10, Folder 180-188)
  - #855 - 881 (Box 11, Folder 189-196)
  - #882 - 905 (Box 12, Folder 197-205)
  - #906 - 927 (Box 13, Folder 206-213)
  - #928 - 963 (Box 14, Folder 214-223)
  - #964 - 999 (Box 15, Folder 224-233)
  - #1000 - 1035 (Box 16, Folder 234-244)
  - #1036 - 1078 (Box 17, Folder 245-255)
  - #1079 - 1089, 1098 - 1120 (Box 18, Folder 256-265)
  - #1121 - 1156 (Box 19, Folder 266-276)
  - #1157 - 1184 (Box 20, Folder 277-286)
  - #1185 - 1222 (Box 21, Folder 287-298)
- Other Writings, Notes, and Memorabilia, 1887-1945; Series III; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series is arranged with all other writings at the beginning in chronological order. These writings are followed by notes, with memorabilia at the end of the series.
  - Other writings
    - 1895, 1929-1936 1895, 1929-1936 (Box 22, Folder 299-322)
    - 1937-1939 1937-1939 (Box 23, Folder 323-338)
    - 1939-1941, 1944, undated 1939-1941, 1944, undated (Box 24, Folder 339-353)
    - undated undated (Box 25, Folder 354-355)
  - Church history: notes, 1903-1942, undated (Box 25, Folder 356)
  - Cathedral Church of St. John the Divine, New York City: notes, [ca. 1924-1929] (Box 25, Folder 357)
  - Numismatics: notes, 1940, undated (Box 25, Folder 358)
  - Miscellaneous notes, writings, undated (Box 25, Folder 359)
  - Memorabilia, obituaries, memorial tributes, 1887, 1918, 1944-1945 (Box 25, Folder 360)